okay welcome back this is part three the last part
好的，欢迎回来，这是第三部分，也是最后一部分
um here we're gonna get into some real nitty-gritty puzzle construction and design stuff
在这一部分，我们将探讨一些关于谜题构造与设计的一些真正重要的细节
um so you know this is the meat of the talk really um
你懂的，这部分才真正是这次讲座的重点
lesson number 21 is “speak playfully to the solver”
第21课是 「与解题者愉快地交谈」
（译者注：Akari Puzzle，中文叫《点灯游戏》、《点亮游戏》、《数灯》，由Nikoli于2001年首次发布）
and uh to illustrate this I want to show you an akari puzzle
为了说明这一点，我想给你们看一个《点灯游戏》（Akari Puzzle）
akari is a puzzle type where you're given a grid it's a logic puzzle
点灯游戏是一种逻辑解谜，里面会给你一个网格
and there's some cells that have different numbers in them
有些格子里会有不同的数字
and the goal is to place light bulbs in the grid in some of the empty cells
目标是在一些空格子里放上灯泡
and there are three rules
有三条规则
one is that the lights shine horizontally and vertically and your goal is to cover the whole grid to illuminate the whole grid using lights
第一条，灯泡会水平和垂直地照亮一行和一列，而你的目标是用灯光照亮整个网格
however there are two constraints
但是有两个限制
one is two lights are not allowed to illuminate each other
一是两盏灯不允许互相照亮到对方
and the second is the numbers on the grid tell you the the number of lights adjacent to that number in the sort of north south east west directions
二是，网格上的数字告诉你该格子上下左右相邻的灯泡数量
so, a two for example like this one has two lights next to it here and here
比如说，这个数字2，旁边有两盏灯，这里和这里
and this one has one light next to it there and so on that's it
这个1旁边就有一盏灯，就是这样
um so I want to show you the solution to this puzzle
我想给你们展示下这个谜题的解答过程
uh and we will observe some remarkable things
我们将观察到一些了不起的事情
um so this is a site called puzzlink where you can play a lot of these types of logic puzzles
这谁一个叫做puzz.link的网站，里面你可以玩到很多这种类型的逻辑谜题
um and we'll take you through the solution
我将带你过一遍解答过程
at first actually this is this is a somewhat difficult puzzle
首先，这是个有点难度的谜题
this is not necessarily a completely beginner level puzzle
这并不是一个初级的谜题
at first you may not find any immediate location to make progress
一开始你可能找不到任何一个直接看得出来的位置来取得进展
but one thing to look at is this one in the corner
但值得注意的是这个角落里的1
and so, we know that there's either a light bulb here or here
我们知道要么有个灯泡在这里，要么在这里
but we don't know which of those two it is yet
但我们还不能确定是其中哪一个
however, one thing we can deduce is that there cannot be a light bulb here
然而，我们可以推出的是，这里是不可能有灯泡的
because if there was a light bulb here then both this cell and that cell will be ruled out from having a light bulb
因为如果这里有一个灯泡，那么这个还有那个格子都不能有灯泡
because two light bulbs cannot illuminate each other
因为两个灯泡不能互相照亮对方
um therefore there can't be a light bulb here
因此这里不可能有一个灯泡
and so, using a dot we can mark this cell as a cell that doesn't have a light bulb
所以我们用一个小点来代表这里不能有灯泡
another way of seeing this is that if there was a light bulb there or a light bulb there
从另一个角度来看这个问题，如果这里有个灯泡，或那里有个灯泡
in both cases this cell is ruled out from containing a light bulb
在这两种情况下，这个格子都被排除在外
therefore in both cases there's no light bulb here
因此，在这两种情况下，这里都不能有灯泡
we can make similar progress by looking at this two here
我们可以用类似的方法来看这个2
there's sort of three candidate locations where a light bulb could be
这里有三个候选位置来放灯泡
but only two of them will contain light bulbs
但其中只有两个会放灯泡
however we can deduce that this cell right here cannot contain a light bulb
然而，我们可以推断出，这一格不可能包含灯泡
otherwise there would only be one other space left adjacent to this too because these two cells would both be ruled out
否则这个2旁边就只剩一个能放灯泡的格子了，因为这两格都被覆盖了
therefore there cannot be a light bulb here
因此这里不可能有灯泡
and so, knowing that these two cells cannot be light bulbs allows us to make additional progress
所以，知道这两格不能放灯泡让我们有了更多的进展
if we look at this two right down here we may also deduce that this cell can't be a light bulb
如果我们看一下下面这个2，我们也能推断出这一格不能有灯泡
because again it would rule out two possible locations of the three that could be light bulbs
因为它也把三个格子中的两个位置给覆盖掉了
therefore there's no light bulb there
因此那里不能放灯泡
similarly there's no light bulb here because it would rule out those two cells leaving only one place remaining for another light bulb adjacent to this two
同样地，这里也不能有灯泡，因为它将覆盖掉这两格，只剩下一个与这个2相邻的位置了
so there's no light bulb there
所以这里不能有灯泡
and now we can look at this one and do similar logic
现在我们可以看这个1，做类似的逻辑
there can't be a light bulb here because it would rule out both of these, therefore that's not a light bulb
这里不能有灯泡，因为它将覆盖这两格，所以不能有灯泡
and that chains into the next two and now we can't have a light bulb here or here because they would both rule out too many locations
然后逻辑链走到下个2，这里或这里都不能有灯泡，因为它们覆盖掉了太多位置
and using the same type of chaining logic we could see on this two there can't be light bulbs here and there
用同样的逻辑链，我们可以看到，对于这个2，这里和这里不能有灯泡
and then this dot implies that for this one there can't be a light bulb there
然后这个点表明，对于这个1，那里不能有灯泡
and then this two is then implied that there are no light bulbs here or here
然后这个2，这里和这里也不能有灯泡
and now on this one we can learn that there's no light bulb here
然后对这个1，我们知道这里不能有灯泡
and on this one we can learn that there's no light bulb here because again it would rule out all the possible locations where a light bulb could be
然后对于这个1，我们知道这里不能有灯泡，因为一样的，它会覆盖所有可选位置
and then these two dots together imply that we can't have a light bulb here because it would rule out the only remaining locations next to this one
然后这两个点一起表明了，在这里不能放灯泡，因为它将覆盖掉这个1旁边仅剩位置
and the chaining keeps going this two rules out that
逻辑链还可以进行下去，这2排除掉这个
this two rules out these two
这2排除了这两个
that one is now ruled out from here
那个1排除掉这个
this dot that we did earlier also rules out this side
我们之前这个点也排除了这边这个
and now finally after all that setup after all that work we finally have this one over here
现在，终于在所有这些准备工作之后，我们终于有了这边这个1
where both sides of it have been ruled out
它的两边都已经被排除了
and we can finally place our first light bulb in the puzzle
而我们终于可以把第一个灯泡放进去了
and after that placing that light bulb in the puzzle we can place the light bulb next to this one
放了这个灯泡之后，我们就可以放这个1旁边的灯泡
we could place the two light bulbs next to this two
我们能放这两个灯泡在这个2旁边
which then allow us to place the two light bulbs next to this two
然后这就让我们可以在这个2旁边放这两个灯泡
which allow us to place the light bulb next to this one
然后又可以在这个1旁边放这个灯泡
and then these two
然后这两个
and then this one
然后这一个
and then these two
然后是这两个
and these two
和这两个
and this one
和这一个
and these two
和这两个
and it just keeps going until we place the last two next to these
一直到我们把最后这个两个放进去
and to finish the puzzle there is one square remaining that hasn't been illuminated
要完成这个谜题，还剩一个格子没被照亮
and of course we have to put the final light bulb there
当然了，我们得把最后一个灯泡放在这里
and that is the solution to this Akari puzzle
而这就是这个点灯游戏的解法
and there are so many things about this puzzle that are remarkable
这个谜题里有很多了不起的地方
um you know there's this whole sense of playfulness
你知道，整个过程有一种很有乐趣的感觉
as you're going through the puzzle and taking these steps one leading to the next leading to the next
你在解决这个谜题的过程中，做了这样一些步骤，一个接一个的，前一个解释了下一个
there's this repeated pattern or motif where you're using the same lemma or the same uh pattern or technique over and over again to create this chain repetition of logic
有这样一个重复的模式，你一遍又一遍用同样的规律或技巧来创造这样一个逻辑链
um and then there's a variant or a twist on that lemma where you know you're using it once and then a second time on the same thing
然后这样的规律又有一个变体或转变，你在同一事物上使用了一次然后又用第二次
um and there's the whole setup and payoff like you do one lap around the grid to rule out one set of spaces and then you do a second lap which rules out a second set of spaces
还有这整个的布置，就像你绕着格子过一趟，排除了些地方，然后又过一遍，又排除了一组格子
and then results in the final placement of the light bulbs
然后得到了灯泡的最终位置
the whole surprise ending where there's only one space left is sort of um a cherry on top
而最后只剩下一个空格这样一个惊喜的结局，又有点锦上添花的感觉
but you know you look at a puzzle like this and there can be no doubt that it was created by a human
但你看到这样的谜题时，毫无疑问它是由人类创作的
this puzzle is just like it's beautiful
这个谜题的设计就很美丽
（译者注：《超级马里奥：3D》的设计师 林田宏一 所提出的四步关卡设计法，即「起承転結」（起承转合），引入、发展、转折和总结）
um there's some steps of how it's created that feel a little bit similar to sort of the Nintendo 4 step level design
它的制作步骤有点类似于任天堂的四步关卡设计法
where you have something new and then you sort of introduce it and then create a twist on it and then um you know put it together to into a finale
也就是你有些新的东西，然后引入它，再创造一个转折点，再合到一起成为结局
uh and then you know you might throw away this idea for your next puzzle
然后再下个谜题中你可能会抛弃这个想法
um but there's something special going on here
但这里面也发生着一些很特别的事情
and it makes the experience of solving this puzzle more than just one of um you know finding the answer or something
而这使得解谜的体验不仅仅是去找到答案
it's like communicating with the author of this puzzle
它就像是在和这个谜题的作者交流一样
and I’ll share with you a quote from Nobuhiko Kanamoto who was the editor of Nikoli
我和你们分享Nikoli的编辑Nobuhiko Kanamoto的一段话
and this is way back this is two decades ago before sudoku took over in the west
这是二十年前的一段话了，那时候数独还没在西方流行开来
this is when sudoku that was computer generated was just starting to come out
正是计算机生成的数独刚刚开始出现的时候
and um Kanamoto-san remarks that computer-generated sudoku puzzles are sort of lacking that vital ingredient that makes puzzles enjoyable this sense of communication
Kanamoto先生指出：“计算机生成的数独谜题缺少一种使谜题玩起来很愉悦的重要因素，
即缺少解题者和创作者之间的交流感”
and you know what ended up happening was these sort of massive uh numbers of computer-generated sudoku puzzles flooded the newspapers in the west and the puzzle books in the west
你知道，后来的结果是，大量计算机生成的数独谜题充斥着西方的报纸和谜题书籍
and as a result um you know subscribers of Nikoli and other Japanese puzzle magazines
而结果，你知道，Nikoli还有其他日本谜题杂志的订阅者们
they had this sort of taste for handcrafted puzzles
他们对手工制作的谜题有了一定的品味
uh but folks in the west never developed that taste they were just bombarded with computer-generated puzzles
但西方人从来没有发展出这种品味，只会被电脑生成的谜题“轰炸”
which uh is sort of a tragedy in some ways
这在某种程度上是个悲剧
because the subtlety and excitement of really good sudoku puzzles or other paper-based logic puzzles um has been lost
因为真正好的数独或其他纸质逻辑谜题的精巧性和刺激性已经丧失了
and a lot of people think of sudoku as sort of a tired boring not that interesting not that novel puzzle
很多人都认为数独是一种乏味的、无趣的、没有新意的谜题
um but there are good sudokus this is a book uh by Thomas Snyder called the art of sudoku
但也有好的数独，这本书是Thomas Snyder写的，叫做《数独的艺术》(The Art of Sudoku)
and uh it's just one of many examples
这只是其中一个例子
but the puzzles in this book they're not only artfully designed and laid out
这本书中的谜题不仅有艺术性的设计和布局
but they also have this sort of flow between the puzzle maker and solver
而且其中有种解谜者和设计者之间流畅的交流
where you're taking on a journey from starting the puzzle to the end where more and more things are revealed to you
你就像开启了一段旅程，从起点到终点，里面的东西逐渐揭示给你
and if you've never done a good sudoku puzzle I would highly recommend you actually try them um
如果你从来没有做过一个好的数独谜题，我强烈建议你去试试
better yet go on “cracking the cryptic” YouTube channel and look at some of the more interesting sudokus that they've done
可以去“Cracking The Cryptic”这个油管频道看看，他们做了些非常有趣的数独谜题
and give them a try yourself um
然后再自己试试
but you know the question is how do you design puzzles like that
但你知道，我们的问题是，我们如何才能设计这样的谜题？
and there is a trick there is a technique that allows us to do that
有一个诀窍和技巧可以让我们做到这一点
and it's um well the technique is called “designing from the front” aka “forward design”
这个技巧叫做「从正面设计」，也即“前向设计”
and I will show you a demo of this
我给你们演示一下
um and we're going to open up the creator for these types of puzzles
我把这个谜题的编辑器模式打开一下
um and I’m literally yoloing it
这里我就冒个险了
like when I did the recording of the GDC talk I sort of had a plan of what I’m going to do
当我在录正式的GDC演讲的时候我提前规划好了要怎么做的
but here I’m literally just going to make it up as I go
但这里，我就直接即兴创作了
and so, we're creating an Akari puzzle
那么，我们是要创作一个点灯游戏
let's make a low difficulty one and insert lots of easy steps
让我们做一个低难度的，插入些简单的步骤
something we might do is let's put in a zero
我们能做的是，我们先放个0进去
a zero is sort of an obvious place to get started
0是一个很明显的可以作为起点的地方
it's a so-called “hook” it's a thing that the player will immediately take their pencil and put in something
这就是一个所谓的引子，是一个能让玩家立即拿起笔填上的东西
um and let me just zoom out a tick
让我缩小一点
the method that we're using here is we're gonna place clues and solve the puzzle at the same time
我们这里要使用的方法是，我们放置线索的同时进行解谜的过程
and we're going to place clues in the order that the player would sort of notice them as they were solving the puzzle
我们要按照玩家在解谜时注意到的顺序来放置线索
so, we flip into answer mode
所以，我们切换到解题模式
and then in answer mode we'll mark these two cells as cells that uh the solver will know are not light bulbs
然后在解题模式中，我们将这两个格子标记为不能放置灯泡的地方
and then we'll go back into edit mode and let's just add some more stuff
然后我们回到编辑模式，再增加一些内容
um you know let's try putting a two here right
我们试着在这里放个2
and then we'll go into answer mode
然后切到解题模式
and the solver will realize okay well after the zero goes there then we have to put two light bulbs there
然后解谜者会意识到，好吧，既然这有0，那么就必须在那里放两个灯泡
let's go back into edit mode let's try putting some walls here and here
让我们回到编辑模式，让我们试着放些墙壁，在这里和这里
this will create a situation where that cell needs to be lit by a light bulb but the only possible location of a light bulb to light it up will be here
这就创造出一种情况，这个格子需要被照亮，但唯一可能的位置是在这里
because anywhere else um you know we can't put a light bulb there
因为其他地方，你知道我们不能把灯泡放在那里
so, then we go back to answer mode and we stick a light bulb there
所以我们回到解题模式，在那里放一个灯泡
uh let's see what else let's try putting a wall here
呃，我们看看还有什么，我们试试在这里放一面墙
and maybe these two light bulbs we want them to infer together the next step
也许，对于这两个灯泡，我们想要让它们一起推出下一步
and let's try uh let's try putting a two here uh
让我们试试，呃，让我们试试在这里放一个2
and then our solver upon sort of seeing the top and bottom of this two have been ruled out
然后解谜者看到这个2的上面和下面都被排除了
can put two more light bulbs there and there
就能在这里和这里放两个灯泡
uh okay pretty good
呃，好的，不错
now we're gonna have to make sure like we can't put a block there otherwise it will have invalidated that part of the solution
现在我们要确保我们不会在这里放一个墙，否则就会使之前那块解失效了
so, we kind of have to keep in mind uh what are the bits that are required to sort of make the puzzle that we've done so far work
所以我们必须记得让我们目前的谜题生效的那些部分
um but you know if we feel that uh the lights are shining too far and we need to add more obstacles
如果感觉灯光覆盖得太远了，我们需要加一些障碍
we could add some obstacles on this side let's say
我们可以在这一边增加一些障碍物，比如说
um you know I’m not sure what we're going to do there
我还不知道要在这里做什么
maybe uh well let's see we could try uh we could try putting a 1 here
也许...让我看看，我们可以试试...我们可以试试在这里放一个1
and that will allow us to rule out these two cells
这样我们就可以排除掉这两个格子了
now that we've put one there can that do something interesting uh
既然我们已经放了个1，这能带来什么有趣的事情呢
well we could maybe put a block there and then we know a light bulb has to go in the corner
也许我们可以在这里放一个墙，然后我们知道必须放一个灯泡在角落里
uh sure let's do that because that you know these two cells both have to be lit up but we can't put one there
我们这么做吧，因为这两个格子都得被点亮，但我们不能放在这里
maybe this could also reveal something to us uh
或许这能揭示些东西
let's try let's try something a little more sophisticated here
让我们试试些更复杂的东西吧
let's copy the trick from that previous Akari puzzle whereby
让我们借鉴一下之前那个点灯谜题的技巧
because one side of this two has been blocked
由于这个2的一边已经被覆盖了
we know that this can't be a light bulb and this can't be a light bulb
我们知道这里不能放灯泡，这里也不行
because either of these would rule out too many spots and the two would only have one location left
因为这两种情况都会排除掉太多位置，使得这个2旁边只剩一个位置了
so, let's try that
所以，我们试试这么做
then we learned that these are not light bulbs
然后我们知道，这些地方不能放灯泡
let's try well we could try putting a two there and then we'll place those two there
让我们试试，我们可以试着在那里放个2，然后这两个灯泡就在这里
which then feed back into the two that we were just in and give us two light bulbs there and there
然后这就能反馈到我们之前那个2，这样就确定了在这里和这里的两个灯泡
lovely
很不错
uh what now and you can see how this just flows like I’m literally just making this up as I go I do not have a plan
现在你可以看到这一切是如何流畅进行的，我其实就是即兴发挥的，没有一个计划
um maybe I could have a plan and I could try to make a puzzle that has a certain pattern or goes around the grid in a certain way
也许我可以有个计划，我可以试着做一个有某种模式的谜题，或者以某种方式绕着网格走
like maybe I want the flow to kind of go in a circle and come into the middle that can be a nice motif
比如我想让这个解谜的过程绕成一个圈，然后最后到中间来，这是一个不错的模式
let's try doing that so let's make it so this one kind of goes up and gives us some logic in the upward direction
让我们把它做成这样，这个1能给我们一下关于上面的逻辑
like maybe this one and this one can combine and we can have uh let's try and think let's put a number there maybe
也许这两个可以一起，我们能…让我想想，我们也许在这里放个数字
maybe a one and maybe all three of these combine to force a light bulb uh in the upward direction there
也许是个1，也许这三个一起就使得在上面必须有个灯泡
whoops answer mode boom
噢，点错了
um and now this will sort of push logic horizontally
现在我们得让逻辑链往水平方向发展
let's see we could we could put one here maybe we could put a one here
让我看看，我们可以在这里放个1
and then we have that one
然后放这个灯泡
maybe these two then are going to combine together
也许这两个灯泡能一起（推出后面的结果）
i mean we can we can reuse tricks in a new setting or we could have new tricks or we could have the same tricks
我们可以在新的环境下复用之前的技巧，或者也可以用新的技巧
and all of these will take the solver on a different journey depending on what we want to do
而所有这些都会把解谜者带入一个不同的旅程，这取决于我们想做什么
you know if we want to be artful and we want to have a certain sort of a plan to create something spectacular we can do that
如果我们想要艺术性，想要按某种计划来创造一种看起来令人惊叹的东西，我们可以这样做
but we can also just make something flowy and simple and fast that is easy to solve and players can get through quickly
但我们也可以就做一些流畅的、简单的、快速的、容易解决的、玩家可以快速完成的东西
it all depends on what we're feeling like or what we want to do
这一切都取决于我们的感觉或我们想做什么
let's see so that was the most recent one that I put in
让我们看看，这是我刚放进去的那一个
I want that to force something
我希望这个能迫使一些地方
I haven't really decided what we could we could try something that can be interesting is is to create uh let's see here uh
我还没决定怎么做，我们可以尝试一些有趣的东西，就是创造...让我看看...
well let's just try putting a two here and blocking off a few things maybe that
好吧，让我试着在这个放个2，然后加点墙来挡住一些东西
so that will well do we want to have this so open I guess that's okay
这样就可以了，我们想要让这部分敞开吗？我想应该可以
uh we'll force a few of these like that and then maybe we can put one like that
我们可以就像这样迫使一些地方…然后也许我们可以像这样放个墙
we could even put a zero here which will then mean we cannot put one there
我们甚至可以在这里放一个0，这样就意味着我们不能在放灯泡了
something that's interesting sometimes is to have a long row where you can't put light bulbs anywhere on them
有时候这种很长一整排都不能放灯泡的情况是很有趣的
for example say I put a zero here
比如说我在这里放一个0
and then let's see we can block this off we don't need that
然后让我看看，我们可以把这个挡住，我们不需要这个
but then the zero will rule out all of these
但这个0会排除所有的这些地方
and then if you look at this the only place this can be illuminated is by placing a light bulb here
然后你可以看到，唯一能照亮这个地方的就是在这里放一个灯泡
uh boom and the only place where this cell can be illuminated by placing a light bulb in that cell itself boom
然后要把这个格子照亮就得在它本身放个灯泡
maybe we can do this one more time
也许我们可以再做一次
if we put a zero here then that will rule out this
如果我们在这里放个0，那么就可以排除这个
and then the only way that cell can be illuminated is by putting a light bulb here
然后唯一可以照亮这个格子的方法就是在这里放一个灯泡
uh whoops uh boom okay um
噢，又点错了
how's that working pretty good I didn't need this for anything
效果如何？很好。我不需要这个东西了
maybe I want this light bulb to infer something in the middle
也许我想让这个灯泡推断出中间的一些东西来
trying to think of a good way to do that um
我在想一个好办法来做到这个事情
did we need that? maybe we could just have a two here
我们需要这个吗？也许我们可以在这里放一个2
and then we will have to put two light bulbs there
然后我们要在这里放两个灯泡
and then maybe this is where the final light bulb goes to eliminate that one
然后也许这就是最后那一个灯泡的位置，来照亮那个格子
and we can check our answer
接着我们可以检查一下我们的答案
now uh you know we we erased and and re-added a bunch of things so we really should check our whole solution in order to confirm that the the logic flow is intact
现在我们应该检查一下整个解，以确认逻辑流程是完整的
and the way to do that is erase our answer and do a complete test solve
做的方法是，我们擦掉我们的答案然后做一个完整的测试过程
so, let's just pretend we're solving the puzzle
那么，假装我们在解这个谜题
you know I would do all this
你知道，我会做这样一些
is there anything I can deduce right now there actually is I can put a light bulb here
有什么我现在就能推断出的吗？事实上，我可以在这里放个灯泡
because I know that this cell has to be illuminated and nothing else can light it up
因为我知道这个格子必须被照亮，而其他地方都不行
you know does that spoil the aesthetic of my puzzle going all the way around
这会破坏我之前设计的绕整个网格一圈的逻辑流的美感吗？
well maybe i might decide to fix this or I might decide I just don't care that's fine
好吧，我可能会决定去修复这个问题，或者我也可能决定不管它，问题不大
but the intended first step was here
但我们设计的第一步是在这里
and then we can get this light bulb uh
然后我们可以得到这个灯泡
sometimes it's interesting to think like what if the player doesn't see this move
有时候想一下如果玩家没有看到应该这样走该怎么办？这还挺有意思的
like what if the solver just has to go somewhere else can they make progress elsewhere
比如说，如果解题者得从别的位置继续，那他们能在别的位置取得进展吗？
um like you might notice that you can't put two here because that would violate the one
你可能会注意到，你不能在里放两个灯泡，因为那会违反这个1
and we need sort of two of these three to be lit up
我们需要在三个中的两个位置放灯泡
and therefore, this one if it wasn't lit up would force this which would be a contradiction
因此，如果这个位置没有灯泡，那么就会迫使这里形成矛盾
and so, this one has to be lit up
所以，这里必须放灯泡
does that help me move forward I’m not sure I think I still need to know which one of these two it is
这能帮助我们取得进展吗？还不确定，我想我还是需要知道这两个里面选哪一个
and so that would allow me to make that discovery
那就会让我取得这样一个发现
and then so we get that we get that
然后我们得到了这个，又得到了这个
we said that would give us this
这会让我们得到这个
which would give us this
又让我们得到这个
um and then this 2 gives us that
然后这个2又让我们确定了这个
that one gives us those two
那个1又确定了这两个
which gives us that
这又让我们确定了那个
which then gives us this to sort of force that
然后确定了这个，固定了那个
which then gives us this to force that and that's sort of just an add-on
这就让我们确定了这个
then those two which finally reveal where that final light bulb in this row has to go
然后是这两个，这就最终揭示了这排我们需要放置的最后那个灯泡
which is there
就是那里
so, most of our solution path is intact
所以，我们的解法的大部分路径都是完整的
there's maybe a few places where we could skip ahead a little bit
也许有几个地方我们可以跳过去一点儿
do we want to go back back and fix it
我们需要回去修复它吗？
we could if we were really trying to go for a specific uh look or a specific theme
我们可以这么做，如果我们真的是想追求一个特定的形式或主题的话
but the point is you have a lot of freedom as a puzzle designer to create that
但关键点还是，作为一个谜题设计师，你有很大的自由来创造这些东西
and this method of designing from the front or forward design allows you to really have quite tight control over the solution experience of the person solving the puzzle
这种从正面设计的方法，或者说前向设计，可以让你对解谜者的解谜体验有严格的控制
uh if you do it correctly and if you're good at it which is is hard right
前提是你做得对或者你很擅长这一点的话。但这很难，对嘛？
like i've been doing this for many years so I have some experience with this
比如说，我已经做了很多年了，所以我会有些经验
and you know i have a sense of like where it could go wrong or what types of assumptions i should and shouldn't make when i'm making these sort of you know when i'm adding a new square to the grid
当我在网格中添加东西时，我会对哪里可能出错、我应不应该做出什么样的假设有一定的感觉
how is this going to affect the solution path based on what i've created so far
以及基于我目前所创造的东西，这将如何影响解谜路径？
and you have to have a good sense of how these puzzles solve in order to be able to do that
你得对这些谜题的解法有一个很好的感觉，才能做到这一点
so, some of the best composers of these puzzles are also the best solvers of them
所以，一些最好的谜题创作者也是最好的解谜者
because they themselves are able to once they place one thing in the grid they can deduce exactly all that can be deduced from it
因为一旦他们自己在网格中添加什么东西，他们就能准确推导出所有能被推导出的东西
and therefore, have a really good understanding of what the solver experience is going to be
因此他们也就对解题者的体验有很好的了解
um with logic puzzles that's true
对逻辑解谜来说是这样的
although it's less true with other types of puzzles like crosswords um
尽管对于其他类型的谜题，比如填字游戏，可能就不完全是这样了
I think there's a famous mike sellinger quote
我想Mike Sellinger曾经说过一句著名的话
where he says um you know making a good crossword versus solving a crossword is is like arson versus firefighting
他说：“创作一个好的填字游戏之于解填字游戏，就如同纵火之于救火”
and it's not necessary that the same person is going to be it's not necessarily true that the same person is going to be good at both arson and firefighting
同一个人不一定就得同时擅长纵火和救火
but with logic puzzles I think it often is
但对于逻辑谜题来说，我认为大部分情况是这样的
anyways I’m going to close this don't need to save it
无论如何，我要把这个给关了，不需要保存
so, designing from the front has a number of benefits
所以，从正面设计有很多好处
uh you know you can control the flow
你知道你可以控制解谜流程
you can create these playful setups
你可以创造这些有趣的设置
and you can hide eureka moments in really interesting ways
你可以用非常有趣的方式来隐藏尤里卡时刻
another thing that designing from the front enables is this sort of deductive solution where as a solver you're making logical deductions you're never guessing right
从正面设计带来的另一个好处是，作为解谜者，你在进行逻辑推理而不是在猜测，是吧？
like when you solve a sudoku you generally aren't guessing you're putting in a number once you're confident that that's true
就当你在解数独时，你一般不是在猜测，而是一旦你确信这是对的，就填入一个数字
and that means that once you get to the end and you found a unique solution you're sort of aware that it is unique
这意味着，一旦你走到了最后，你找到了个独特的解法，你会意识到它既是独特的
because in solving the puzzle deductively you have established that uniqueness
因为在通过推理解谜的过程中，你已经建立起了这种唯一性
and this can be a source of pleasure as a solver
而作为解谜者，这可能就是一个快乐的来源
because it's it's sort of like the soundness and completeness meeting together implying that both the existence and uniqueness of the puzzle have been established
因为这类似于说，可靠性和完备性同时满足，就意味着谜题的存在性和独特性都被确立了
and that's different than a puzzle where you guess and you find the answer and you don't even know is this the unique answer is this the only answer
这与那种猜答案的谜题不同，那种谜题里面你找到了答案而你甚至不能确定是不是唯一的答案
you know this definitively is the unique answer and you had to find it by sort of going through the motions that were uh intended for you to go through
（而这种谜题）是肯定有唯一答案的，因为你得通过一套规定动作来找到它
um and that is what enables this communication because you know that this is what the puzzle designer intended you to do when you're solving it
而这就是促成这种交流的原因，因为你知道这就是谜题设计者希望你在解题时做的事情
and you're consciously aware of that
而你也清楚地意识到这一点
and the the puzzle designer is surprising you with what the next step is and how it's been laid out and not just with the you know what the actual solution is
谜题设计者通过下一步是什么和怎么布置的，而不只是用实际的解法是什么来带给你惊喜
the the surprising thing at the end of the puzzle isn't what the final grid looks like when it's done
在谜题的最后，令人惊喜的事情并不是最后的网格看起来是什么样子的
it's what was the logic that enabled you to deduce that that was the only way it could be
而是让你能推断出这是唯一方法的逻辑是什么
and that is is the thing that elevates these types of logic puzzles to a greater aesthetic than a computer generated sudoku
而这正是将这类逻辑谜题提升到比计算机生成的数独有更高的审美境界的原因所在
one of the important things to do is make the key move or sort of the key step that you have to do provably unique
而你需要做的很重要的一点是，「让谜题的关键步骤可被证明是独一无二的」
if we go back to that um chess puzzle by Sam Lloyd,
让我们回到Sam Lloyd那个国际象棋谜题
king e2 is the only way to achieve that mate in three
其中王e2是实现三步内将杀的唯一途径（即王往左上方走一格）
and the fact that that's true kind of forces the puzzle uh the puzzle forces the solver to uncover the planned eureka moment that has been set up um
而这一事实，意味着这个谜题迫使解谜者去发现这一设定好的尤里卡时刻
and in chess you know sometimes there's different responses
在实际下棋中，你知道对手可能会有不同的反应
like if the player goes king e2 uh the opponent playing black does not have to respond by queening the pawn
比如说，如果白方王e2，那黑方不一定就会把兵升变为后
the player the opponent can respond by just moving a bishop or doing something else right
对方可以通过移动象或其他事情来回击，是吧？
and in all of those cases the player does have mate in three
在所有这种情况下，肯定都可以三步内将杀对面
but the most interesting part of the puzzle is sort of what do you do against the most challenging response
但谜题最有趣的部分应该是你如何去应对最有挑战性的回击
and so, the fact that there's one key move on the first move is essential in all chess puzzles
因此，第一步棋是关键步对所有国际象棋谜题来说都是必不可少的
it's sort of a requirement of the genre there needs to be a single unique key move on turn one
第一步棋有一个独特的关键走法，算是这种类型谜题的要求
but then often in subsequent turns it can sort of fork and branch a little bit more depending on what the opponent does
但在随后的汇合中，就会根据对方的行动而出现分支
and it's not you know you need to kind of find a response to everything right
对每一种对手的行动你都需要找到一种回应方式
so, the fact that the later part of the puzzle may not be unique because of what the opponent can do
所以，尽管谜题后半部分可能因为对手的下法，并不是独一无二的
doesn't spoil the aesthetics of the puzzle having a unique key move
但这并不影响谜题拥有独一无二的关键一步的美感
puzzles that lack a unique key move are often called “cooked puzzles” meaning you know as in “his goose is cooked”
缺乏独一无二的关键步骤的谜题通常被称为”cooked puzzle”，来自”his goose is cooked”中的”cooked”
it's just like not a good puzzle or it's not worthy of being printed
这就意味着它不是一道好谜题，或者说它不值得印刷出来
a second solution is often called a “dual”
（谜题的）第二种解法通常被称为“Dual”
or in video games I’ve heard it called an “exploit”
或者在电子游戏中我听说这被叫做“exploit”（秘技/卡bug）
where the player can get around the intended thing that the developer was trying to force them to do but the player is somehow able to find an exploit to avoid doing this
也就是玩家通过找到了某种方式或漏洞，绕过了开发者试图强迫他们做的事情
and if the purpose of your puzzle is to conceal a unique eureka moment,
如果你的谜题的目的是为了隐藏一个独特的尤里卡时刻
then intentionally having multiple solutions is not a good idea
那么故意提供多种解法就不是一个好主意
and accidentally having multiple solutions may be a problem that you know you want your QA to catch
而意外地拥有多种解法，可能就是你希望你的测试人员能够发现的问题
if you're doing puzzle design you want to make sure that your test solvers are really good at finding those multiple solutions
如果你在做谜题设计，你要确保你的测试人员擅长找到那些多重解法
and the way you want them to do that is by being deductive solvers that can really try and establish the uniqueness of every solution by proving it
你想让他们做到，成为推理型的解题者，能够真正通过证明的方式来确定每个解的唯一性
um and that's hard for some types of puzzles especially uh very stateful puzzles like block pushing puzzles
而这对于某些类型的谜题来说是很难的，尤其是像推箱子这种状态很多的谜题
where there's a million different states that the puzzle can be in and it's often very hard to determine that an alternative way of solving the puzzle is impossible
那里面有无数种不同的状态，通常很难确定出现另一种解法是不是不可能的
you really want to as a puzzle designer make sure you're slicing off those Rabbit Trails
作为一个谜题设计者，你得确保你把那些Rabbit Trails给去除掉
and just making it so that you don't have to check too deep in order to make sure that something doesn't happen
这样你就不必为了确保某些事情不发生而检查得太深
I can give you a million examples of these which I didn't include in the talk
我可以给你举出无数个例子，我之前没把这个包含在演讲里
I think the one that sticks with me the most is in steven's sausage roll they have this level called the tower
我想最让我印象深刻的例子是在《史蒂芬香肠卷》中，有个叫“The Tower”的关卡
where there's eight sausages stacked up and you have to sort of set them up in this unique way
那里面有八个香肠堆在一起，而你得以一种特别的方式把它们摆好
um but the way I solved that puzzle was not the intended way
但我解决这个谜题的方式并不是开发者设计的方式
and the way a number of people solved it I’ve checked on YouTube and twitch videos was really not the intended way
我看油管和Twitch上很多人也不是用的开发者设计的方式
um I mean they ultimately got to the same final state but the sort of setup or the way they went about going about the setup to get there uh can vary in a lot of ways
他们最终是到达了相同的最终状态，但他们达成的方式却是不尽相同的
and some of the setups are really convoluted like the thing that I did was kind of really complex and annoying and difficult to set up and painful
有些方法真的很复杂，就像我的方法，真的很复杂凡人，而且很难做到、很痛苦
whereas there was a nice intended solution to the puzzle but I never even saw it during my first playthrough
而它本身开发者设计的是一个很好的解法，但在我玩的一周目中我甚至没见到过这种解法
I basically had to cheat and look up the answer before I learned what the intended solution was
我恐怕得通过作弊或者查找答案才能知道预定的解法是什么
and I think my experience playing that game would have been a lot better if I had been coerced toward the intended solution more strongly
我想，如果我被更有力地迫使去寻找预定解法的话，我玩这个游戏的体验会好很多
anyways like deductive puzzles kind of need to have unique solutions
总之，逻辑推理型的谜题还是需要有独一无二的解法的
because the flow demands that you sort of prove every step you're not guessing right
因为解谜的流程就要求你去证明每一步，毕竟你不是在猜测，是吧？
so you need to be able to prove every step that you move forward on and therefore you have to just end up with one solution at the end
所以你每前进一步都需要做出证明，因此必须在最后只得到一个解法
you wouldn't be able to have deductive flow if the solution wasn't unique
如果解法不唯一的话，你就不可能有一个演绎推理的思维流
um so many types of puzzles chess puzzles logic puzzles etc. demand solutions
所以，许多类型的谜题，如象棋棋谜，逻辑谜题等，都需要（独一无二的）解法
but many other types of puzzles ought to have unique solutions
但是许多其他类型的谜题也应该有唯一的解法
because of the aesthetics and because of the need to have a unique eureka moment and to force that on the player
因为需要一个独特的尤里卡时刻并将其带给玩家
unique solutions are just a way to facilitate that
唯一的解法正是促进这一目标的一种方式
so, I advocate uniqueness whenever somebody asks me
所以，每当有人问我，我都主张解法要有唯一性
you know and for those point-and-click adventure games that have multiple solutions to some puzzles
你知道，对于那些其中谜题有多种解法的点击冒险游戏来说
that can be okay like
（有多种解法）可能问题不大
there are there are many downsides right like you're doing extra work that the player might not even see
但也有很多坏处，比如你是在做一些玩家可能根本看不到的无用功
um sometimes you'll end up with an extra item and not even know what it was for
有时你在游戏中会得到一个额外的物品，但你甚至不知道它是用来做什么的
um you know like oh that was for the second possible solution to that puzzle and you never used it
你知道，那是给那个谜题的第二种解法用的，但你从来没有用过它
like you want to have this feeling of every item in the game having had a purpose right
你会想有这样的感觉，游戏中的每件物品都应该有一个用途，对吗？
like I got that thing what was it for um
就比如我得到了那个东西，那它有什么用呢？
if you leave the game without feeling that you understood that purpose
如果你在离开游戏时，没有感觉到你理解了那个物品的用途
then sometimes it can feel a little incomplete or it feels like you know the communication was lost at some point um
那有时就会感觉到有点不完整，或者就像感觉从某一刻起你失去了与开发者之间的交流
you know so there's a lot to think about with regards to uniqueness
所以关于唯一性的问题还是有很多东西需要思考的
moving on let's talk about themes
继续下一课，我们来谈一谈“主题”
adding a theme to puzzles can bring value in many different ways
为谜题添加一个主题可以在很多方面带来价值
one example that I will give are burr puzzles or kumiki puzzles
我举一个例子，就是一般的孔明锁（Burr Puzzle）和“組木”（Kumiki Puzzle）
kumiki puzzles are Japanese animal themed burr puzzles
組木 是日本的以动物为主题的孔明锁
I have one right here
我这里就有一个
this is sort of themed as a pig
这个是以猪为主题的
uh I can show you too it's a cool puzzle
我给你看看，这是一个很酷的谜题
it's cute it's not particularly difficult
很可爱，也不是特别难
but it has this move where you have to press the nose in
但它有个操作，你必须得把鼻子按进去
and then that's what's required to sort of get out the first piece uh
然后才能取出第一块组件
you press the nose in and it's just kind of quaint and clever
你得把鼻子按进去，这设计得很巧妙、聪明
um as opposed to just a regular old burr puzzle which is uh you know just a bunch of wooden sticks that you have to notch together
而左边普通的孔明锁，相比较起来就是一堆木棍，你得把它们拼合在一起
there's something a little bit more
右边的谜题有些更多的东西
and uh it can also help you kind of remember what you're doing
而且它还能帮助你记住正在做什么
like when you have the pieces laid out on the table and you're trying to put this thing back together
比如说你把所有的组件放在桌子上，你想把这个东西拼起来的时候
um you realize well okay that's the ears that's the legs
你会意识到，好吧，那个是耳朵，那个是腿
that's the you know the language of where things go and how things fit together uh can somehow uh be easier if the theme is there
如果有主题的话，就会形成关于这个谜题的语言，拼起来也更简单一下
uh I’ll show you a couple of other examples these are slitherlinks
我给你看几个其他的例子，这些是数回谜题
on the left is one by Serkan Yürekli and this was done for the Indian national puzzle championship uh maybe like six seven years ago
左边这个是Serkan Yürekli为印度全国谜题锦标赛设计的，大概6、7年前做的
it's done in the theme of I’m not sure if it's a lily pad or a lotus flower or some kind of uh elaborate geometric design
它的主题是...... 我不确定这是睡莲还是莲花，或者是某种精心设计的几何图形
but that design actually makes the slitherlinks puzzle more interesting
但这一设计实际上使得数回谜题更有趣
like there is a vertex of degree 17 in the middle of this puzzle which you know you never see in a normal uh slither link with square geometry
比如这个谜题中间有个17度的顶点，在普通方形的数回谜题中是看不到的
and sort of these two twos over here and the way they uh relate to this degree high degree vertex in the middle that's actually the break into this puzzle
而这里的两个2，它们如何与中间这个点的度数相关的，正是这个谜题的突破点
the essential part of the solution is to kind of work out how that might function
而这个谜题最关键的点就是找出这部分是如何起作用的
um and so it's not just aesthetic for the sake of aesthetics it also lends itself to the solution the puzzle which is amazing
所以这不仅仅为了美学的目的，这也支持着这个谜题的解，这很了不起
the one on the right is a slitherlink puzzle
右边这个也是一个数回谜题
where the 0,1,2, and 3 numbers have been replaced by the four letters M, O, A, Y in some order
0,1,2,3这几个数字被M,O,A,Y这四个字母按一定顺序取代了
and figuring out that order is part of the puzzle
而弄清这个顺序也是谜题的一部分
um and this was also published on Mother’s Day on grandmaster puzzles
这个谜题是在母亲节那天发表在Grandmaster Puzzles上的
and it has the words mama mommy you know in in in a bunch of uh corners of the grid
上面有“MAMA”“MOMMY”的字样，在角落里
you know mama is there like it's just kind of cute and clever and interesting
这是一种有点可爱、聪明、有趣的设计
but it's also a valid slitherlink
但它也是一个有效的数回谜题
uh and you know it just adds some little bit of extra sparkle or spice to this puzzle
这就给谜题带来了些额外的Sparkle和趣味
um another benefit is like when you're creating these puzzles
另一个好处是，当你创作谜题的时候
sometimes you know it's like a blank page you don't know what to do what you want to create
有时你就像拿出了一张白纸，你不知道该做什么，你想创造什么
and coming up with a good theme can lead you in the direction of uh concretizing your ideas
而想出一个好的主题可以引导你把你的想法具体化
and having some kind of uh you know key thing to frame your puzzle around
以及给你一些你可以围绕着表达的关键点
like themes allow you to have a purpose to your puzzle
就像说主题可以让你的谜题有一个目的
beyond just you know make one more of the same type of logic puzzle or crossword puzzle or you know wood puzzle whatever it is you're making
而不仅仅是做一个相同类型的逻辑谜题或填字游戏或木制谜题之类的
so, you get this additional aesthetic value but it's also useful as a constructor to be able to have them
所以，你得到了额外的美学价值，但作为创作者，拥有主题（对构造谜题）也是很有用的
it also makes the puzzles more memorable
它也让谜题更容易被记住
because you know everybody knows oh that like 17 degrees slitherlink or that mother's day puzzle right
因为，比如说，每个人都能记得那个17度的数回或那个母亲节的谜题，对吗？
it uh gives a short description to the puzzle and allows it to have a place in your brain where it sort of sticks out
它为谜题提供了一个简短的描述，让它在你的大脑中占有一席之地，让它变得更加突出
the converse to that is "don't be clever in ways that the solver will never notice"
而与之相反的是「不要在解谜者注意不到的地方耍小聪明」
uh there are some themes that people think of as an idea for a crossword that uh maybe make the crossword worse
有一些人们可能认为是填字游戏的主题，可能实际上会让谜题变得更糟
here's a crossword
这里有个填字游戏
uh it's actually quite a remarkable construction
这实际上是个很了不起的构造
it is a quintuple pangram meaning every letter of the alphabet from a to z has been used five times in this grid
这是一个“Quintuple Pangram”，意思是从A到Z每个字母都正好用了5次
so, you will notice there are five Q’s in the grid there are five X’s and there are five Z’s and five J's and so on like
所以，你会注意到网格中有五个Q，五个X，五个Z，五个J，等等
so really uh the constructor here had to get in a lot of interesting words
所以，创作者必须得在这里面加入很多有趣的词语
you could see like so five Qs means there are ten keywords in this uh crossword
你可以看到五个Q意味着这个字谜里有十个关键词里有Q
because they are both across and down um
因为既有横着的也有竖着的
so, you know there's barbecue and square feet and quirk
所以你知道，这里有Barbecue（烤肉）、SQFT（square feet平方英尺）
and quack and quintuple and
Quirk（怪癖）、Quack（呱呱叫）、Quintuple（五元组）
quick and downquark uh q-tip right
Quick（快）、Downquark（下夸克）、Q-TIP
so, a lot of interesting and flavorful q words
所以，有很多有趣的有意思的含q的词
but there's also some words that are kind of not that great that that you wouldn't want in a crossword
但也有一些词不是很好，是那种你不会想在填字游戏中出现的词
there's dxix for example like what is that
比如说DXIX，那是什么？
I will show you in a moment um let's
我待会给你们看
I’ll share this quote with you which is from the late Nancy Salomon who passed away just a couple of months ago
我和你们分享下这段话，这来自已故的Nancy Salomon，她在几个月前刚刚去世
（译者注：Sage Advice这篇博客可以在cruciverb.com上搜索到，这是供新手填字游戏创作者学习的一篇文章）
she is a godmother to all crossword creators with her famous sage advice uh blog um
她是所有填字游戏创作者的教母，有这样一篇著名的叫“Sage Advice”的博客
（译者注：这句话我个人是这么理解的，如果有误还望指正）
you know she shares that "a plethora of X’s, Z’s, Q’s, J’s and the like will buy you nothing but rejections if you pay too high a price for them."
她分享说：
“如果你为过多的X、Z、Q、J单词付出太多的代价，这只会让你的填字游戏被出版商退稿”
and so, here's a couple of examples
所以，这里面有这么几个例子
（译者注：Albuquerque 阿尔伯克基/阿尔布开克/阿布奎基，是新墨西哥州最大的城市）
one clue is Albuquerque’s home and the answer is NMEX
一个谜面是“阿尔伯克基的所在地”，答案是NMEX
like it's supposed to be the state of New Mexico
这个答案本来应该是 新墨西哥州（New Mexico）
but who writes NMEX for New Mexico, like you might write NM
但谁会把新墨西哥州缩写成NMEX，最多也就写成NM
uh this is kind of a weird abbreviation that feels kind of off and wrong
这是一种奇怪的缩写，感觉有点不对、不太行
and is that really the answer you want in your crossword?
这真的是你在填字游戏中想要的答案吗？
you know the DXIX is 519 in old Rome it is a Roman numeral clue
而DXIX则是罗马数字的519，这是个罗马数字的线索
and let me tell you that the number of times you've seen these if you've been doing crosswords long enough it always elicits a groan
让我告诉你，如果你玩填字游戏的时间够久，每次见到这种线索，总会引起一声叹息
and it's always like well I guess if you had to if you really had to but like putting numbers in a crossword grid is kind of
我想如果你真的不得不这么做…但把数字放到填字游戏里有点…
you know once you've seen it once, you've seen it
你懂得，一旦你见过一次，你也就见过了
and like the point is you're paying sort of in the sparkle and the liveliness of the clues and the quality of the fill uh in order to achieve this goal of a quintuple pangram
重点是，你为了达到每个字母用五次的目标，你牺牲了谜题的闪光点、生动性和质量
so, the question is like you know what is what are you willing to do for your art right?
所以，问题是，为了艺术性你愿意付出什么？
and are you making this as something that is designed to be pleasurable for the solver or are you making this as a work of art
你是为了让解谜者感到愉悦，还是把它当作一件艺术品来做？
maybe if you're making this as a work of art then it's worth it
如果你把它作为一件艺术作品，那么它就值得
but if your goal is to make it as something that's pleasurable for the solver then you've got to be a little bit careful
但如果你的目标是让解谜者感到愉悦，那你就得小心一点了
this puzzle is by David C. Duncan Dekker and it is a remarkable puzzle
这道谜题的作者是David C. Duncan Dekker，而这是一道了不起的谜题
and I think that as far as a quintuple pangram goes it's not that bad like there's actually some good words in here
我认为就每个字母用五次这种谜题而言，它并没有那么糟糕，这里面还是有些好词的
it's mostly lively fill there's not too many like really tenuous ones
大部分都是充满生动性的词，没有太多浅薄的词
but there are some and it's just unavoidable when you're trying to achieve a goal this lofty
但总还是有一些的，而这是当你想实现如此高的目标时所难以避免的
I can think of all the puzzles that I’ve like wasted hours and hours trying to finish
我回想我那些浪费了很多时间来尝试创作的谜题
it was because I was trying to achieve some kind of aesthetic goal that was just not cooperating
那都是因为我试图达到某种美学目标，但却难以与其他方面配合到一起
and I tried one thing and it didn't work tried another thing didn't work
我试了一件事，但没有成功，又试了另一件事也没有成功
and constantly having to back out and a lesson hard learned is to not make your goals too difficult
只能一次次放弃，而我学到的一个惨痛教训是，不要让你的目标太难以实现
and especially not to compromise on the quality of the puzzle in order to achieve them
尤其是不要为了实现这些目标而牺牲了谜题的质量
I will show you one more example this is the cast elk puzzle
我再给你看一个例子，这是“Cast Elk”
where is it I had it on my desk at some point is it on my shelf
它放到哪里去了…它之前在我桌子上…在书架上吗
it's hiding my desk has a lot of stuff on it where is it
它藏起来了…我桌子上有很多东西…它在哪里
there it is okay uh here we go
在这里，好吧
so, this is a puzzle called the Cast Elk it's published by Hanayama
所以，这是一个由Hanayama发售的一个叫“Cast Elk”的谜题
uh it's actually a really cool puzzle
这其实是个非常酷的谜题
so, there's these two uh they're basically interlocked semicircular sort of c-shaped rings that are themed like a deer with antlers
有这样两个扣起来的半圆形的，有点类似C形的环，是以带着鹿角的鹿为主题的
or an elk I guess you know is what it's called
或者说应该说是麋鹿，你知道它名字就是这么叫的
and you kind of have to slip them past each other and then sort of like rotate them sideways a bit and then they come apart
你必须把它滑过对方，然后把它们侧向旋转一下，然后它们就分开了
and you can reverse that to push them back together
你可以反着这个过程来把它们又扣起来
the thing that's interesting about these is that well my spouse Alissa had this as a teenager
这里面有趣的是…我的配偶Alissa在十几岁时就有这个东西了
and she was able to solve the puzzle but she never actually noticed the trick
她能够解决这个谜题，但她从来没有注意到其中的窍门
and the trick is that when you have these two things together um and you try to slip when you try to do this move
诀窍是当这两部分扣起来时，当你试图做这个操作时
it actually most of the time will not work uh
大多数情况下是不会成功的
and it's because these uh sort of tips of the antlers uh are not all the same length uh
这是因为这些鹿角的尖端并不都是一样长的
there are two antler tips in this that are shorter than all of the rest
这里面有两个鹿角的尖端比其他的都要短
and when you have this interlock c-shape there's four kind of ways of taking it apart
当这两个C型的部分互扣着的时候，有四种方式可以把它们拆开
that seem like they're isometric but they're actually not
看起来像是等距的，但实际上不是的
because the antlers are not the same length
因为鹿角的长度是不一样的
so my spouse spent her teenage years not realizing why sometimes she could solve this puzzle and sometimes not
所以我的配偶在她十几岁的时候并没有意识到为什么她有时能解开，有时又不能
and when you go to put it back together it's even worse
而当你把它拼起来的时候，情况就更糟糕了
because there's actually eight possible ways of putting it together only one of which works
因为实际上有八种可能的组合方式，只有一种可行
um and so it's kind of like a cruel joke played by the puzzle designer
所以这有点像谜题设计师开的一个残酷的玩笑
and if you're in on it it's great you know once you know the secret it seems clever
一旦你知道了这个秘密就会觉得这看起来很聪明
but when you're solving it. it just seems kind of like a bit baffling and it can leave you with this feeling of like not really understanding what the intent of the puzzle designer was
但当你解开它的时候，就会觉得有点困惑，会让你感觉到不明白谜题设计者的意图是什么
um and so I think the lesson is that it would be great if after you solved this puzzle
所以我觉得，如果在你解开这个谜题后
you could sort of open a fortune cookie and learn by the way the secret is this um
你能够类似于打开幸运饼干，顺便了解一下这个秘密，那就还不错
because understanding that secret is sort of having the eureka moment
因为理解了这个秘密，就有了尤里卡时刻
and if you solve the puzzle without having a eureka moment
如果你解开了这个谜题，却没有尤里卡的时刻
then uh part of the aesthetic value of that puzzle is lost on you
那么这个谜题的一部分美学价值就会消失了
and I can't count the number of times where I’ve watched somebody solve a video game puzzle
我已经数不清有多少次看到有人解决一个电子游戏的谜题时
and they accidentally find the solution and move on and they're sort of missing out on the beauty that lies within that puzzle
他们是意外地找到了答案，然后就往前走了，他们就错过了那道谜题中美丽的部分
because they haven't discovered that the deeper secret lying within
因为他们没有发现隐藏在其中的更深的秘密
and I mean many video game puzzles simply do not have a deeper secret lying within
其实很多电子游戏根本就没有更深层次的秘密
but when they do I think you know my goal is always to allow the player to experience that deeper secret to let them in on the joke
但如果有的话，我想我的目标是让玩家体验到更深层次的秘密
to sort of maximize their exposure to the eureka moment
去让他们最大限度地接触到尤里卡时刻
even if it means telling them afterwards what is the thing that they were supposed to have figured out
即使这意味着在事后告诉他们自己本应该发现的东西
because to me experiencing the eureka moment is the important part of the puzzle
因为对我来说，体验尤里卡时刻是谜题的重要部分
now maybe you want to leave that secret in there
或许你想把这个秘密留在那里
maybe you want it to be something that somebody can come back to
也许你想让它成为别人可以回味的东西
maybe you want it to be you know a book
也许你想让它成为那种，类似于一本书
that when you read it the second time you learn a little bit more
当你读第二遍的时候，你会学到一点更多的东西
there's a little bit of depth that you can uncover in the second reading right
有一些你能够在第二次阅读时发现的深度，对吗？
that could be an option too but it's just something to think about
这也是一个选项，但这也得好好经过思考
and you know that's the end of this example I guess
那么这个例子就到此为止了
Next lesson is “the format changes everything”
下一课是「形式会改变一切」
I want to show you a few examples of puzzles that are almost all the same
我给你们看几个例子，这些谜题几乎都一样
these are all puzzles where you have to draw a path that sort of goes through everything on the grid
这些谜题都要求你必须画出穿过网格上所有东西的一条路径
and so, on this left this is a puzzle called simple loop
左上角这个谜题叫《Simple Loop》
it's a paper-based logic puzzle you have to draw a loop that passes through every tile exactly once not including the shaded ones
这是一个纸质的逻辑解谜，你必须画一个环，经过每一个格子且只经过一次，不包括阴影部分
this one on the bottom left is from a game called blossom tales
左下角这个谜题来自于一个叫《花之传说》（Blossom Tales）的游戏
and it's sort of the same puzzle except there's an entrance at the top and an exit at the bottom
它也差不多是一样的谜题，只不过上面有一个入口，下面有一个出口
this one in the middle is from the witness and it's the same except there's an entrance and an exit
中间这个来自《见证者》，基本上也是一样的，除了有个入口和出口
and you only have to collect all the dots you don't actually have to visit sort of every vertex of the grid
而且只需要经过所有的点就行了，不用经过网格的每个顶点
this one on the right has multiple entrances and exits and you may not know where they are
右边这个有多个入口和出口，你可能不知道它们在哪里
this is from a mobile puzzle game called alcazar
这是一个叫《Alcazar》的解谜手游
and it seems like they're all similar
看起来它们都很相似
but there's actually a lot of differences in the solver experience when you're solving these puzzles
但实际上当你解这些谜题时，体验有很大不同
um you know the modality of your input and the output that you're being shown right
比如你的输入和输出显示的形式（不同）
whether you're seeing a screen or seeing something physically in front of you or doing something on paper
不论你看到的是屏幕，还是看到的实体的物品，或者说在纸上解谜
whether you're using even controller versus keyboard mouse versus touch
不论你用的是手柄还是键盘，鼠标还是触摸屏
they all provide different affordances like can you click and drag do you have to move a cursor around to select which square you're on
它们都提供了不同的能力，比如你能点击拖动吗，你需要移动光标来选择吗
are you on a small screen or a big screen how big is the text of your puzzle
是在小屏幕还是大屏幕上，谜题的文字有多大
um can you undo and restart can you save your progress
可以撤销和重启吗，可以保存进度吗
on paper you have to literally use an eraser
在纸上你需要用橡皮擦
but you can also use multiple colors of pencils to maybe make a guess and try something out
但你也可以用多种颜色的铅笔来做出猜测或者尝试
and then you know what you want to erase uh when you're uh done making that guess and decided that's not the way forward
之后你就需要擦除一些东西
some video games have undo systems where you can make a move and go back some don't
有的电子游戏有撤销的操作，你可以做一个操作然后回到上一步，而有的游戏没有
some are brutal blossom tales actually if you step off the path onto those red zones
有的又很残酷，《花之传说》里面如果你走到红格子上了
you take damage and you have to restart
你会受到伤害，而且你必须重新开始
and there's no undo meaning that if you don't solve the puzzle correctly on the first try you actually are hurt
没有撤销就意味着如果你一次没有做出正确尝试，你就会受到伤害
you know when I got to this puzzle I literally just print screened it and turned it into MS paint and solved it in there
当时我解这个谜题的时候，我是截屏然后放到画图里面，先在里面把它解出来
punishment of mistakes is sort of an interesting aspect
对错误的惩罚是一个有趣的方面
like some puzzle games if you go back to the early uh like early 90s chip’s challenge style puzzly adventure games
如果你回到上世纪90年代早期，那种《Chip’s Challenge》风格的冒险解密游戏
which had some real time and some turn-based elements
里面有些实时的和回合制的元素
many of those games were very punishing
这些游戏中很多的惩罚都非常重
like if you stepped the wrong way you'd have to completely restart the whole level you'd lose a life it was very frustrating
如果你走错了，你就得重新开始整个关卡或者丢失一条命，这让人很沮丧
um nowadays I think fewer games have that aesthetic
我觉得现在有这种审美的游戏越来越少了
and they're more uh you know they're more about solving the puzzles about their eureka moments
现在的游戏更多是关注在解谜上，关注尤里卡时刻
and they allow undo and reset and you can often even undo your reset
而且它们允许撤销和重置，你甚至可以撤销你的重置
which can be useful if you hit it by mistake um
如果你不小心按到重置按钮的话，这就很有用
another big one is note taking and we'll get to this in the next section
另一个重要的方面是做笔记，我们会在下一节中讨论这个问题
but essentially what I mean by note-taking is in the witness you just have to draw a line from the start to the end you can't sort of draw a partial line on the corner of the grid
但本质上说，在《见证者》中，你必须从头到尾画完整的一条先，你不能只画一部分的线
whereas in alcazar the way you're making progress is by um sort of adding little bits of lines slowly until you've drawn in the whole path
而在《Alcazar》中，你是一点点加上小线段，知道你画出整条路径
and the experience of solving those two puzzles is very different
而解决这两个谜题的体验是非常不同的
Note-taking can increase depth and this is you know an important enough uh lesson to be a number of its own
「记笔记可以增加深度」，这一点还比较重要，值得单独列出来
I want to show you an example in sudoku and then we will go back to the path drawing puzzles
我想给你们看一个数独的例子，然后我们再回来看前面画线谜题的例子
a lot of players have had different ways of doing sudoku notation but they're sort of three that are most in in common use
很多玩家都有不同的方法来做数独的记号，但这是最常用的三种
uh and many sudoku solvers are using all three of these notations at once
还有许多数独解题者同时使用这三种记法
they're sort of candidate notation meaning this cell must contain one of these numbers
一种是候选记号（Candidate notation），意思是格子中一定是这些数字之一
you know seven two means this cell is either a seven or a two
写成“72”就意味着这个格子里要么是7要么是2
uh Snyder notation is sort of the reverse it's this number goes in one of these cells
而Snyder记号是一种相反的记号，就是这个数字要放到这些格子中的一个位置
like here's a box the two in this box goes in one of these cells
比如有这么个框，2就会放入这个框中的其中一格
and sometimes you sort of draw a two on the border between two boxes it's sometimes called a bivalue
有时你会在两个框交界的地方写个2，这有时被叫做“bivalue”
there's different ways that people do it and annotate it
人们有不同的方法来做这样的记号和注释
and then there are colors which means these two cells are the same number but I don't know which one they are yet
然后还有涂色记号，意味着两个格子数字相同，但还不确定是什么数字
um and this is an example from cracking the cryptic where here Mark Goodlife is filling out this grid
这里这个例子来自Cracking the Cryptic频道，Mark Goodlife正在填这个格子
（译者注：这是一个温度计数独，含温度计的格子从头部开始数字增大）
and hasn't put in a single number yet or he's just put in his first number which is a seven over here uh in this thermometer
还没有填上一个数字，或者说他刚刚填了第一个数字，也就是这个温度计里的7
and uh it took him 30 minutes to get this far
他走到当前这个状态花了30分钟
but after he put in that seven he was then able to finish the whole puzzle in less than a minute
但当他填入7后，他就能在一分钟内完成整个谜题
because as soon as you get one number the whole thing collapses um
因为一旦你得到一个数字，整个谜题就会“崩塌”
but this type of puzzle would not be solvable without note taking
但这种类型的谜题如果不做笔记的话是无法解决的
like you can't solve it the way you would in normal sudoku where you're just putting in one number then the next then the next then the next then the next
你不能像普通的数独游戏那样，先填一个数字，然后再一个接一个填
you need to be able to take notes and sort of reduce the possibility space down from this large you know
你需要做笔记，把这么大的可能性空间给缩小
so many things could be the answer down to only these things could be the answer
从很多东西都可以是答案，到只有这些才是答案
and then from there you realize ah this number has to go there
然后你就会意识到，这个数字一定要放在那里
um and so the eureka moments that are possible with note taking are much deeper than those without it
所以，含有记笔记过程的尤里卡时刻，要比那些没有的要深刻得多
let's go back to the witness this is an example from it's very early in the game
让我们回到《见证者》来，这是游戏前期的一个例子
in fact that you see this puzzle and there's multiple start locations multiple places where you could possibly end it
事实上，你看到这个谜题之后会发现，它有多个起点和终点
the goal is basically you have to draw a single line from one of those start locations to an end location that both passes through all these black hexagons
目标是你必须从其中一个起点位置画一条线到终点，同时穿过所有这些黑色的六边形
as well as um well it has to cut the light and dark cells uh so that they don't live in the same connected component
同时还得把含有黑块和白块的格子分隔开来，使得它们在不同的连通分量当中
and there's a long uh you know definition of what that really is but it sort of is like keeping all the light cells on the left and dark cells on the right or vice versa it's similar to that
基本上就是说让所有含黑块的格子在线一边，含有白块的格子在线的另一边
um and if you sort of take this puzzle into MS paint
而如果你把这个谜题截屏放到画图里面看
you could kind of draw in some little bits of deductive analysis of where the path must go
你就可以推理分析出一些小线段来代表路径必须经过的地方
and from here you can actually solve the puzzle pretty easily
而根据这个你可以很容易地解决这个谜题
uh but that's sort of not really the way this puzzle is designed right
但这个谜题设计出来并不是这样的方式，对吗？
it's not a puzzle where you can enter partial bits of progress while playing it
这不是那种你玩的时候一小截一小截线段往里添加的谜题
it's a puzzle game where you sort of start at the beginning and then draw a line out and it goes through everything and exits
这是你得从起点开始画一条线、穿过所有东西直到终点的谜题
this isn't necessarily a bad thing but it does limit the complexity of the types of puzzles that you could create in the witness
这不一定是件坏事，但它也的确限制了《见证者》中能创作的谜题的复杂性
like if you go back to this Alcazar puzzle on the right hand side here
就比如我们回到之前那个《Alcazar》的谜题，在右手边这个
you could never make this in the puzzle in the witness because it would just be too frustrating for players
你永远不可能在《见证者》中做这样一个谜题，因为这会让玩家非常懊恼
like they would literally need to print screen it and go into paint because you can't necessarily solve it start to end without making a mistake
你真的可能得截个屏然后放到画图里来看，你不可能从头到尾不犯错画根线就把它解出来了
um it's just sort of too much for the player's working memory to be able to do that in their head right
这对玩家的短期记忆能力来说实在是太多了，不可能就在脑海里完成这个任务
it's too big of a grid for you to be able to head solve
这个网格太大了，不可能在脑海里解出来的
and so, the witness fundamentally limits itself to smaller grids
因此，《见证者》从根本上说限制了自己只能使用较小一点的网格
because it wants to you know have grids that people can head solve
因为它希望它的网格能直接让人在脑海里解出来
rather than grids that people are going to need to take a million notes for
而不是需要人们去做无数的笔记
but that sort of limits how deep and interesting those puzzles can be
但这同时也限制那些谜题的深度和趣味性
now that said taking notes isn't necessarily a good fit for the theme of the witness
虽然这么说，但做笔记本身不一定适合《见证者》的主题
the witness is fundamentally a game about drawing a line from one place to the next
《见证者》从根本上说就是从一点到另一点画线的游戏
and not a game about note-taking when you're solving logic puzzles
而不是要求边解逻辑谜题边做笔记的游戏
um so I think the witnesses approach is correct for what the witness is trying to do
所以我认为《见证者》的方法对于《见证者》本身所要尝试做的事情来说，是正确的
um but I’m just saying it does create some limitation in what types of puzzles can be expressed
但我还是得说它对能够表达的谜题类型产生了一些限制
or you know can be expressed in a way that's convenient for the solver to access
或者说（它限制了）那种能够用让玩家可以方便解出来的方式表达的
without copy pasting the puzzle into MS paint or taking notes on paper or trying to keep way too many things in their head at once
而不需要把谜题粘贴到画图中，或者在纸上做笔记，或者在脑海中记太多东西的谜题
some puzzles are basically designed such that note taking is the solution to the puzzle
而有些谜题基本上就是把记笔记作为谜题的解决步骤
minesweeper is one of them
扫雷就是其中之一
if you try solving minesweeper without noting the mines it's really hard
如果你试着不标记地雷的位置来解开扫雷，那真的很困难
but also even just noting where the numbers are that is the form of progress of the puzzle
但即便只是去留意数字的位置，那也是解谜取得进展的一种形式
like note-taking is progress it feels like progress
记笔记就是一种进展，它感觉上就像取得了进展一样
uh for these types of zebra crossing or Einstein’s riddle type puzzles
对于这种《斑马难题》
where they give you a bunch of uh sort of logical hints and then you have to fill in the grid
里面给你一些逻辑线索，然后你得填上这个表格
like you know who had the milk who had the water you know who was what color etc
比如给你线索说，谁喜欢喝牛奶，谁喜欢喝水，谁的房子是什么颜色等等
those types of puzzles that the note taking is the progress it's what you're doing when you're solving the puzzle
对这种类型的谜题，记笔记就是取得进展，就是你在解谜时做的事情
and this is often true of many types of logic puzzles and paper logic puzzles
很多类型的逻辑谜题和纸质逻辑谜题都是如此
and it is a tradition that isn't used as much in video game puzzles that sort of rely more on statefulness and interaction
而这一传统在电子游戏谜题中并不常有，电子游戏谜题更依赖于状态和交互
because that you know this is a natural fit to pen and paper
因为你知道，（做笔记）很自然地使用于纸上游戏
it's less of a natural fit when you're playing a game and moving a character around in three-dimensional space
但当你在三维空间中移动一个角色时，它就不那么自然了
but they do a good job of making note-taking feel like progress
不过（纸上游戏）在让人通过记笔记感到取得进展这方面做得很好
and that's how they're able to access their depth in a way that isn't too annoying
这就是他们如何能够以一种不太令人讨厌的方式拓展它们游戏的深度